Finding Aid for Leslie A. White Papers 1921-1974
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Speeches, lectures, etc.
  - Newspaper clippings concerning White's speech on atomic energy," 1945, 2 folders (Box 16)
  - Radio Talks 1930-1931, 1938 (Box 17)
  - Pennsylvania State University lecture 1959-1960 (Box 17)
  - International Congress of Anthropological and Ethnological Sciences 1963-1964 (Box 17)
  - Lecture at the University of Colorado March 1974, videotape and VHS use copy (Box 17)
  - "The Energy Theory" Lecture #8, N.S.F. Anthropological Institute, University of Colorado August 15, 1968, 1 sound recording reel (Box 17)
- Miscellaneous
  The Miscellaneous series contains material not easily placed elsewhere. Included are the articles that White wrote under the pseudonym of John Steel and travel journals of his wife Mary written in 1936.
  - John Steel Papers (Leslie White pseudonym) (Box 17)
  - John J. Honigmann on White and Cultural Determinism, with White's comments (Box 17)
  - "Lewis H. Morgan and His Detractors" by A.J.P. Taylor Weekly People, March, 1959 (Box 17)
  - Miscellaneous printed material (Box 17)
  - Note cards of personal accomplishments (Box 17)
  - Notecards on Lowie, Malinowski and Ostwald (Box 17)
  - Contract establishing Leslie A. White Memorial Fund (Box 17)
  - Material used in writing biographical sketches of American anthropologists for various reference works
    - Norman D. Humphrey (1911-1955) (Box 17)
    - Alexander A. Goldenweiser (1880-1940) (Box 17)
    - Elsie Clews Parsons (1875-1941). (Box 17)
    - Alfred L. Kroeber (Box 17)
    - Correspondence with Encyclopedia Britannica, 1958-1969 (Box 17)
  - Travel journals, of Mary P. White 1936 (Box 17)
  - Programs, miscellaneous correspondence, etc. (Box 17)
  - Notebooks on American anthropologists and the history of American anthropology (Box 17)
- Field Notes and Research trips
  Field Notes and Research Trips consists of White's Pueblo Indian research notes and his accumulated material on the life and career of Lewis Henry Morgan.
  - Research notes concerning Pueblo Indians and research trips (Box 18)
  - Use of tobacco by Pueblo Indians 1941-1943 (Box 18)
  - Correspondence concerning the Pueblo of Zia 1958-1960 (Box 18)
  - Papers 1931-1932 concerning ethnological field expedition to the Hopi Pueblo at Oraibi, Arizona (Box 18)
  - Interview with two Acoma Indians accused of murder 1952 (Box 18)
  - Research material-Lewis Henry Morgan (Box 24)
  - Bibliographical notecards listing Morgan correspondence (Box 24)
  - Research material-Lewis Henry Morgan (Box 25)
  - Morgan Correspondence (copies) (A-Z); includes correspondence with Henry R. Schoolcraft and Andrew D. White (Box 25)
  - Research material-Lewis Henry Morgan (Box 26)
  - Research correspondence and articles on the life of Morgan (Box 26)
- Published Material
  Copies of most of White’s books and articles will be found in the Published Materials series. In addition, this series includes reviews of White’s writing, White’s reviews of works by other anthropologists, and correspondence exchange with publishers about his various books and other writings
  - Books by or including articles by Leslie White (Box 19)
  - Books by or including articles by Leslie White (Box 20)
    (continued)
  - Reprints of articles by Leslie White (Box 21)
  - Books and reprints from the Library of Leslie White, including works about White's career and works which influenced White's thought (Box 22)
  - Books and reprints from the Library of Leslie White, including works about White's career and works which influenced White's thought (Box 23)
Selective Index to Correspondents
Adams, Randolph Greenfield, 1892-1951.
1947, 1948, 1949-1950
American Association for the Advancement of Science.
1957-1958
American Folklore Society.
May 21, 1942, Dec. 1942, Dec. 7,1942
Bain, Read, 1892-
1943-1944
Barnes, Harry Elmer, 1889-1968.
In separate folders
Beard, Charles Austin, 1874-1948.
Undated, Sept. 26,1943
Benedict, Ruth, 1887-1948.
Jan. 18, 1928, 1943-1944
Berle, Adolf Augustus, 1895-1971.
1965-1966, 1966-1967
Boas, Franz, 1858-1942.
Apr. 3, 1929
Childe, V. Gordon (Vere Gordon), 1892-1957.
1946, 1947, 1948, 1949-1950, 1953-1954
Cole, Fay-Cooper, 1881-1961.
June 10, 1941, June 30, 1941, Sept. 30, 1941, Apr. 14, 1942, July 23, 1942, 1943-1944, 1947, 1955-1956, 1956-1957, 1958-1959
Connable, Alfred B. (Alfred Barnes), 1904-
1943-1944
Hayakawa, S.I. (Samuel Ichiye), 1906-
Oct. 29, 1969, Jan. 1970, Apr. 1970, June 26, 1970, July 20, 1970, Oct. 21,1970, 1943-1944
Kidder, Alfred Vincent, 1885-1963.
Dec. 21, 1938, Dec. 23, 1940, 1946, 1947, 1950-1951, 1955-1956, 1958-1959, 1962-1963
Kluckhohn, Clyde, 1905-1960.
June 25, 1941, 1943-1944, 1945, 1946, 1947, 1948, 1949, 1949-1950, 1955-1956
Kroeber, A.L. (Alfred Louis), 1876-1960.
Mar. 28, 1929, June 9, 1938, Nov. 10, 1941, Dec. 3, 1941, 1943-1944, 1946, 1947, 1948, 1949, 1949-1950, 1954-1955, 1955-1956, 1956-1957, 1957-1958, 1958-1959, 1959-1960
Levi-Strauss, Claude, 1908-
Nov. 13, 1970
Linton, Ralph, 1893-1953.
Dec. 13, 1938, Feb. 19, 1939, May 30, 1939, June 10, 1939, Dec. 14, 1939, Sept. 13, 1940, Nov. 6, 1940, Nov. 14, 1941, 1942, 1943-1944, 1946, 1947, 1948, 1949-1950, 1950-1951, 1951-1952, 1952-1953
McLuhan, Marshall, 1911-
1962-1963
Mann, Thomas, 1875-1955.
1948
Mead, Margaret, 1901-1978.
1958-1959, 1961-1962
Mencken, H.L. (Henry Louis), 1880-1956.
[In separate folder]
Montagu, Ashley, 1905-
Jan. 19, 1942, 1943-1944, 1948, 1949-1950, 1963-1964, 1964-1965
Mumford, Lewis, 1895-
1949-1950, 1955-1956
Osgood, Cornelius, 1905-
1943-1944, 1948, 1949-1950
Parsons, Elsie Worthington Clews, 1875-1941.
[In separate folder]
Reuther, Walter, 1907-1970.
1949
Sagan, Carl, 1934-
Mar. 5, 1971, Mar. 12, 1971, Apr. 8, 1971, Aug. 3, 1971
Sapir, Edward, 1884-1939.
1921-1930, 1931-1935
Spier,Leslie, 1893-1961.
Oct. 13,1943
Trotsky, Leon, 1879-1940.
Mar. 8, 1939
Vandenberg, Arthur Hendrick, 1907-1968.
1945
Bibliography of books and articles
Undated
"Four Stages in the Evolution of Minding." Evolution After Darwin. Chicago: University of Chicago Press, n.d. p. 239-253.
"Lewis Henry Morgan." Union Worthies, No. 1. Schenectady, N.Y.: Union College, n.d. p.5-9.
1925
"Personality and Culture." The Open Court, 39 (March, 1925): 145-60.
1926
"An Anthropological Approach to the Emotional Factors in Religion." Journal of Philosophy, 23 (September 30, 1926): 546-554.
1927
"Ancient Indians and Modern Pueblos." Hobbies, 8 (December, 1927): 3-19.
1928
"A Comparative Study of Keresan Medicine Societies." Proceedings of the 23rd International Congress of Americanists, (September, 1928): 604-619.
"Summary Report of Field Work at Acoma." American Anthropologist, 30 (October-December, 1928): 559-568.
1929
"Keresan Indian Songs." The Grosvenor Library Bulletin, 11 (March, 1929): 41-43.
1932
The Acoma Indians. 47th Annual Report of the Bureau of American Ethnology, Washington D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1932.
"The Evolution of Culture and the American School of Ethnology." Russian publication, no English copy.
"The Mentality of Primates." Scientific Monthly, 34 (January, 1932): 69-72.
"The Pueblo of San Felipe." Memoirs of the American Anthropological Association, No. 38, 1932.
1937
Extracts from the European Travel Journal of Lewis H. Morgan, edited by Leslie A. White. Rochester Historical Society Publications, No. 16, 1937.
"Some Suggestions for a Program in Anthropology in China." The Chinese Social and Political Science Review, 21(April, 1937): 120-134.
1938
"Science is 'Sciencing'" Philosophy of Science, 5(October, 1938): 369-389.
________. Make Men of Them: Introductory Readings for Cultural Anthropology, ed. Charles C. Hughes. Chicago: Rand McNally, 1972. p. 27-35.
1939
"A Problem in Kinship Terminology." American Anthropologist, 41(October-December): 566-573.
1940
"The Symbol: The Origin and Basis of Human Behavior."Philosophy of Science, 7(October, 1940): 451-463.
________. The Diversity of Religious Symbol. Minneapolis: World Religious Curriculum Development Center, 1974. p. 24-26 (abridged).
________. Humanifestations: Readings in Cultural Anthropology, ed. Jonathan E. Reyman. Champaign, Ill.: Illinois State University, 1973. p. 55-61.
________. Kaleidoscope, ed. Jon M. Shepard. New York: Harper Row, 1973. p. 62-67
________. Language in Form and Idea, ed. T. Bensen Strandness. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1964. p. 137-144.
________. Make Men of Them: Readings for Cultural Anthropology, ed. Charles H. Hughes. Chicago: Rand McNally, 1972. p. 199-205.
________. Sociological Perspectives, ed. Paul E. Mott. Columbus, Ohio: Charles S. Merrill, 1973. p. 116-124.
________. Sociological Perspectives, ed. Scott G. McNall. Boston: Little Brown, 1968. p. 92-101.
1941
"The Cultivation of Cotton by Pueblo Indians of New Mexico." Science, 94 (August, 1941): 162.
"Nicotiana Rustica Cultivated by Pueblo Indians." Science, 94 (July 18, 1941): 64-65.
1942
"Further Data on the Cultivation of Tobacco Among the Pueblo Indians." Science, 96 (July 17, 1942): 59-60.
"The Impersonation of Saints Among the Pueblos." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, Vol. 27, 1942, (1941 Meeting).
"Lewis H. Morgan's Journal of a Trip to Southwestern Colorado and New Mexico, June 21 to August 7, 1878." American Antiquity, Vol. 8, July, 1942.
"The Pueblo of Santa Ana, New Mexico." American Anthropologist, New Series, Vol. 44, No. 4, Part 2. (October-December, 1942).
"On the Use of Tools by Primates." Journal of Comparative Psychology, 34 (December, 1942): 369-374.
1943
"Energy and the Evolution of Culture." American Anthropologist, 45 (July-September, 1943): 335-336.
"Keresan Indian Color Terms." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters, Vol. 28, 1943.
"New Material from Acoma." Smithsonian Institution, Bureau of American Ethnology, Anthropological Papers, No. 32; from Bureau of American Ethnology Bulletin, 136: 301-359.
"Sociology, Physics and Mathematics." American Sociological Review, 8 (August, 1943): 373-379.
1944
"A Ceremonial Vocabulary Among the Pueblos." International Journal of American Linguistics, 10: 161-167.
"Morgan's Attitude Towards Religion and Science." American Anthropologist, 46 (April-June, 1944): 218-230.
"'Rohana' in Pueblo Culture." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts, and Letters, 29: 439-443.
1945
"Diffusion vs. Evolution: An Anti-Evolutionist Fallacy." American Anthropologist, 47 (July-September): 339-356.
"Education: America's Magic." School and Society, 61 (June 2, 1945): 353-354.
"History, Evolution and Functionalism: Three Types of Interpretation of Culture." Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, I (Summer, 1945): 221-248.
"Kroeber's 'Configurations of Cultural Growth." American Anthropologist, 48 (January-March, 1946): 78-93.
"Notes on the Ethnobotany of the Keres." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, Vol. 30, 1945.
1946
"The Origin and Nature of Speech." Twentieth Century English, 1946.
1947
"The Culturological vs. Psychological Interpretations of Human Behavior." American Sociological Review, 12 (December, 1947): 686-698.
"Ethnographic Notes on Sandia Pueblo, New Mexico." Michigan Academy of Science Arts and Letters, 31: 215-222.
"Evolutionary Stages, Progress and the Evaluation of Culture." Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 3 (Autumn, 1947): 166-192.
"Evolutionism and Anti-Evolutionism in American Ethnological Theory." The Calcutta Review, Vols. 104-105: 147-172.
_________. English Summary, n.d.
_________. Translated to Chinese by Ogawa. Minzokugaku Kenkyu, Vol. 15, 1951.
_________. Sociologiá, 10: 1-39.
"Evolution in Cultural Anthropology: A Rejoinder." American Anthropologist, 49 (July-September, 1947): 400-413.
"The Expansion of the Scope of Science." Journal of the Washington Academy of Science, 37 (June 15, 1947): 181-200.
"Human Behavior: Culturological and Psychological Interpretations." Kaleidoscope, ed. Jon M. Shepard. New York: Harper Row, 1973. p.87-92. Adapted from "Culturological vs. Psychological Interpretations of Human Behavior." Sociological Review,12 (December, 1947): 686-698.
"The Locus of Mathematical Reality" An Anthropological Footnote." Philosophy of Science, 4 (October, 1947): 289-303.
"Notes on the Ethnozoology of the Keresan Pueblo Indians." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, 31: 223-243.
1948
"The Definition and Prohibition of Incest." American Anthropologist, 50 (July-September, 1948): 416-435.
_________. Readings in Kinship and Social Structure, ed. Nelson Graeburn. New York: Harper and Row, 1971.
"Ikhnaton: The Great Man vs. the Cultural Process." Journal of the American Oriental Society, 68 (April-June, 1948): 91-114. With a reply by William F. Edgerton and a rejoinder by Leslie A. White, Ibid., 68 (December, 1948): 192-193.
"Man's Control over Civilization: An Anthropocentric Illusion." Scientific Monthly, 66 (March, 1948): 235-247.
"Miscellaneous Notes on the Keresan Pueblos." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, 32: 365-373, (1946 Meeting).
1949
"Energy and the Development of Civilizations." Michigan Technic,(October, 1949): 13.
"Ethnological Theory." Philosophy for the Future, ed. Roy Wood Sellars. New York: Macmillan, 1949. p. 357-384.
"Man's Moment." The Scientific Monthly, Vol. 69; No. 2 (August, 1949).
The Science of Culture. New York: Farrar, Straus and Co., 1949.
_________. Nauka o kulturi. Belgrade, 1970.
_________. La Scienza della Cultura. Firenze: G. C. Sansoni, 1969.
_________. La Ciencia de la Cultura. Buenos Aires: Editorial Paidor, 1966 (?).
1950
"Anthropocentric Illusion." The Calcutta Review, (May, 1950): 81-95.
"The Individual and the Cultural Process." Centennial (1950): 74-80.
1951
"Lewis Henry Morgan's Western Field Trips." American Anthropologist, 53 (January-March, 1951): 11-18.
1957
"The Correspondence Between Lewis Henry Morgan and Joseph Henry." The University of Rochester Library Bulletin, 12 (Winter, 1957): 17-22.
"Evolution and Diffusion". Antiquity, 30: 214-218.
1958
"Culturology." Science, 128 (November 21, 1958): 1246.
"How Morgan Came to Write Systems of Consanguinity and Affinity." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, 42: 257-268, (1956 Meeting).
"What is Classificatory Kinship Term?" Southwestern Journal of Anthropology, 14 (Winter, 1958): 378-385.
1959
"Changing Views." The Unitarian Register, 138 (October, 1959): 9-11.
"Concept of Culture." American Anthropologist, 61: 227-251.
_________. Culture and School, ed. Ronald Shim. Scranton, Penn.: Intext Educational Publishers, 1972. p. 3-28.
_________. The Meaning of Culture, ed. Moris Feilich. Lexington, Mass.: Xerox College Publications, 1972.
_________. Arquivos do Instituto do Antropologia, 2 (March, 1966): 39-71.
"The Concept of Evolution in Cultural Anthropology." Evolution and Anthropology: A Centennial Appraisal. The Anthropological Society of Washington, (May, 1959).
"The Energy Theory of Cultural Development." Readings in Anthropology, ed. M.H. Fried. New York: Thomas Y. Crowell, 1959. Vol. 2, p. 140-146.
_________. Professor Ghurye Felicitation Volume, ed. K.M. Kapadia. Bombay: Popular Book Depot, n.d. p. 1-10.
"A Teoria da Energia No Desenvolvimento Cultural." Sociologia, (1958): 489-500.
The Evolution of Culture. New York: McGraw-Hill, 1959.
The Indian Journals, 1959-1862. By Lewis Henry Morgan, edited with an introduction by Leslie A. White. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1959.
"Man, Culture and Human Beings." Michigan Quarterly Alumnus Review, 66 (December, 1959): 1-6.
1960
Anthropology. By Edward B. Tylor, abridged and with a forward by Leslie A. White. Ann Arbor: University of Michigan Press, 1960.
Correspondencia de Adolfo F. Bandelier, by Leslie A. White and Ignacio Bernal. Mexico: Instituto Nacional de Antropologia e Historia, 1960.
"The World of the Keresan Pueblo Indians." Cultural History, ed. Stanley Diamond. New York: 1960. p. 53-64.
1962
"The Pueblo of Sia, New Mexico." Smithsonian Institute Bureau of American Ethnology Bulletin 184. Washington D.C.: U.S. Government Printing Office, 1962.
1963
"Symboling: A Kind of Behavior." The Journal of Psychology, 53: 311-317. 1963
"The Culturological Revolution." The Colorado Quarterly, 11 (Spring, 1963): 367-382.
"Der Begriff Kultur." Akademische Reihe, ed. Carl August Schmitz. Frankfurt: Akadamische Verlagsgesellschaft, 1963.
"The Ethnography and Ethnology of Franz Boas." Bulletin of the Texas Memorial Museum, No. 6. (April, 1963).
"Individuality and Individualism: A Cultural Interpretation." Individuals in Twentieth Century America: A Symposium Held at the University of Texas in December, 1962. ed. Gordon Mills. Texas Quarterly, (Summer, 1963).
_________. International Journal of Comparative Sociology, 4 (March, 1963): 31-49.
"Keresan Pueblo Prayer Sticks." Papers of the Michigan Academy of Science, Arts and Letters, 48: 549-556.
1965
"Anthropology 1964: Retrospect and Prospect." American Anthropologist, 67 (June, 1965): 629-637.
"Definitions and Concepts of Culture." Concepts, Theory and Explanations in the Behavioral Sciences. New York: Random House, 1966.
"Technology and Economic Development." Economic Development and Cultural Change, 13 (July, 1965): 479-482.
1966
"The Social Organization of Ethnological Studies." Rice University Studies, 52 (Fall, 1966).
1968
"Culturology." International Encyclopedia of the Social Sciences. New York: Crowell, Collier and Macmillan, 1968.
"Harry Elmer Barnes as a Contemporary Encyclopedist." Harry Elmer Barnes: Learned Crusader, ed. Arthur Goddard. Colorado Springs: Ralph Myles Pub., 1968.
"Nations as Sociocultural Systems." Ingenor 5 (Autumn, 1968): 5-8.
1973
The Concept of Culture, by Leslie A. White, with Beth Dillingham. Minneapolis: Burgess Publishing Company, 1973.
Journal of a Trip to the Orient. Houston: Tourmaline Press, 1973.
"Human Culture." Encyclopedia Britannica, 15th ed., 1974. p. 1151-1160.
"Man and Culture." Theories and Paradigms in Contemporary Sociology, ed. Serge Denisoff. Itasca, Ill.: F. E. Peacock Pub., 1974.
1975 (posthumous).
The Concept of Cultural Systems: A Key to Understanding Tribes and Nations. N.Y.: Columbia University Press, 1975.